Testing is the process by which the
code of a program is checked to see
that it works by executing the program
with the aim of finding any errors.
If testing is done successfully then
it should be possible to identify and
remove all the errors from the software.
There are many types of testing which
occur at various stages of development,
such as during the initial coding,
beta-testing before deployment, and
after software roll-out during updates.
Software testing can also happen with
different focus, from individual units
of code [unit testing] by software
developers, to testing how software fares
under different stresses [volume testing].
Broadly speaking, software testing
falls into three categories:
Functional testing, which ensures
that the software operates in
line with the specifications.
Non-functional testing, to test
aspects which are not related
to software architecture such
as performance and reliability
And Maintenance testing, involving testing
post-release to ensure compatibility
with new hardware or software
So why is it important to test code?
Testing is a fundamental
process that helps to create
reliable and usable software.
It helps to check adaptability,
identify errors, avoid future extra
costs and risks, and ultimately
gives confidence in the program.
So, let’s look at some of the
important features related to testing.
Firstly it ‘saves time’.
Timely identification of errors
or bugs means they do not affect
any release dates or deadlines.
Also, it ‘improves efficiency’ as errors
which are caught early on are easier
to remedy, meaning less production
time is wasted as there is not as much
software to trace the error back through.
It also helps improve
‘cost effectiveness’.
Efficient testing means less time
spent solving issues and money lost on
revisions, and this can help prevent
costly failures, as system failures can
have extreme safety and subsequently
financial costs depending on the software.
It ‘improves security’ as
new security threats emerge.
Products must be security tested to make
sure that they are protected against
the latest threats, and by testing when
updating, they can keep up with any
compatibility requirements involved
with updated operating systems etc.
And finally, it helps with ‘consumer
confidence’ as customers are unlikely
to be satisfied if they are delivered
buggy, dysfunctional software and by
testing and eliminating bugs the overall
quality of the product in improved.
Long term it can also help
retain a products viability,
otherwise it may become obsolete.